Finding Aid for Institute for the Humanities (University of Michigan) publications, 1987-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Institute for the Humanities (University of Michigan) publications 1987-1997
University of Michigan. Institute for the Humanities.
9738 Bimu C6 2
Includes annual reports, brochures and pamphlets, course bulletins, calendars, and the newsletters Humanities and Notes from the Institute for the Humanities at the University of Michigan.
0.4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Publications are received on a regular basis. (Donor No. 5895. ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The publications are open for research.
Since World War II there has been an evolution toward a division of knowledge into discrete fields, resulting in ever narrowing areas of scholarly interest and focus. The Institute for the Humanities at the University of Michigan was founded in 1987 partly in response to a recognized need for renewed dialogue across the disciplines. However, it was also developed because there was already evidence of increased intellectual overlap between and among fields in the humanities: literary scholars using the perspectives of anthropology to study the origins of myth; musicologists and art historians using economic history to explain how patronage affected stylistic development; classicists combining the methods of many disciplines in the quest for knowledge of the ancient world. James A. Winn, who was the center's first director, spoke to the synergistic nature of the Institute's mission: "We do not oppose specialization. Instead, we attempt to transcend it by challenging the expert researcher and the innovative theorist to think about their findings on a larger level, as they relate to other investigations in other disciplines, and to excel in original and innovative ways."
The first executive committee, which was formed to assist an appointed director on policy and advise in the selection of internal and visiting fellows and associates, included faculty members from law, romance languages, Japanese studies, music, classics, and history. They, along with interim director John Knott, worked to set the stage for an exemplary interdisciplinary innovation in the humanities and the arts. After several years of planning, the Institute for the Humanities moved into a newly renovated suite of rooms in the Horace H. Rackham Building in September 1987.
While the earliest years primarily focused on building the program, raising an endowment, and increasing the number of fellows, the Institute quickly became a widely recognized center for international scholarship. Under Winn's directorship, the Institute, in just a few years, realized every guiding principle originally envisioned and defined: encourage interdisciplinary discourse and activity; promote the innovative and controversial; build bridges between the creative and performing arts and the analytical work done by humanists; develop an undergraduate dimension; and make findings available to a broad audience. Winn promoted broad, collaborative, integrative teaching in the humanities. Unlike programs elsewhere, the UM initiative, from the start, included a vital teaching component. Fellows developed new pedagogical models for instruction, moved across departmental boundaries, and welcomed students of all levels in their courses.
Institute programs continued to expand and develop. In addition to sponsored courses and mini-courses, key conferences and forums punctuated each term. (Until 1999, conference papers and other program components were oriented around an annual theme.) The Institute's commitment to fostering new connections between the settings in which scholars express themselves and the settings in which artists express themselves resulted in numerous performances each year in theatre, dance and music. Events were framed by panel discussions, brownbag lunches, and lectures.
In 1990, the Institute incorporated into the dialogue the examination of intersections between scientific and humanistic thought. In that year, undergraduate science majors participated in discussions ranging from medical ethics and the behavioral differences among primates, to the implications of technological change for humanists. In 1991, the center innovatively reached out to alumni. A Humanities Camp was instituted. Alumni were invited to a spring weekend of seminars, field trips, lectures and informal gatherings - all oriented around the humanities and designed to showcase some of the best faculty and experiences available at the University of Michigan.
In 1997, as the Institute entered its tenth year, Tom Trautmann, a former fellow, became its second director. In a letter published in the 1996-1997 annual report, Trautmann reaffirmed the center's guiding purpose: "I believe strongly in the Institute's central mission of supporting a community of scholars, both faculty and students, engaged in the creation of knowledge in the humanities."
Directors of the Institute for the Humanities
1987-1988 John R. Knott, Interim Director
1988-1996 James A. Winn, Director
1990-1991 Domna C. Stanton, Acting Director
1996-1997 Diane Kirkpatrick, Interim Director
1997- Tom Trautmann, Director
Institute for the Humanities Annual Themes
1999-2000 Open to Interdisciplinary Proposals
1998-1999 Form and Pattern
1997-1998 Narrative
1996-1997 Images and the Imaginary
1995-1996 Emotion
1994-1995 Work and Play
1993-1994 The Geography of Identity
1992-1993 Utopian Visions
1991-1992 Authority of the Past
1990-1991 Histories of Sexuality
1989-1990 Economies of Art
1988-1989 Translation: Cultural Confrontation and Transformation
1987-1988 Theatre and Society
The Publications includes annual reports, brochures and pamphlets, course bulletins, calendars, and the newsletters Humanities and Notes from the Institute for the Humanities at the University of Michigan. The publications are organized into three series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, and Topical Publications.
The Unit Publications series includes annual reports, brochures and pamphlets, and bulletins describing course offerings from the Institute. This subseries also contains calendars and flyers describing the various programs, presentations, and events sponsored by the Institute for the Humanities. These are arranged chronologically and broken down by the Institute's annual themes. There are two newsletters Humanities and Notes, which cover the activities of the unit from 1989 to the present.
The Sub-Unit Publications series contains brochures from the Humanities Camp. The Humanities Camp is an event which brings together alumni and supporters with University of Michigan faculty to discuss and explore current issues and themes in the humanities.
The Topical Publications series includes Development brochures.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Institute for the Humanities.; Annual reports.; Pamphlets.; Bulletins.; Calendars.; Newsletters.
- Unit Publications
  - Annual Reports, 1987-1998/99, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - Art Exhibitions 1996-1999 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - Course Offerings, 1990-2000, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Calendars
    - Brown Bag Lunch Series, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Annual Theme
      - Histories of Sexuality, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
      - The Authority of the Past, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
      - Utopian Visions, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
      - Geography of Identity, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
      - Work and Play, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
      - Emotion, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - Program Schedule, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - Public Program Schedule
      - Images and the Imaginary, 1997 (Box 1)
      - form and pattern: Trauma, Space, Art, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogs
    - Art at the Institute for the Humanities 1997-1999 (Box 1)
    - Art by University of Michigan Faculty at the Institute for the Humanities, 1996/97 (Box 1)
    - An Art Exhibition at the Institute for the Humanities, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Humanities and the Arts: An Exhibition of Faculty Art, undated (Box 1)
  - Flyers 1987-1997, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Invitations 1990-1995 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - Humanities, 1989-1992 (Box 1)
    - Notes, 1994-2000, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Occasional Papers
    - The Intellectual Economy of Interdisciplinary Scholarship by James A. Winn and Fred L. Bookstein, no. 1, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Utopian Skeletons in the Biometric Closet by Fred L. Bookstein, no. 2, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Posters 1990-1999, undated (Box 1)
  - Programs
    - General 1995 (Box 1)
    - The Mirror of Simple Souls, Libretto by Anne Carson, Music by Jason Kirk, 1999 (Box 1)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  - Humanities Camp
    - Brochures 1993-1999 (Box 1)
- Topical Publications
  - Development
    - Brochures undated (Box 1)